welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
all right check-ins I'm about 15%
nervous the drop down to about 13
percent saying that I'm a little like
just bodily just exhausted at the moment
and I feel sort of like a kinship with
Michael right now because he seems
exhausted as well so the gratitude going
on there so welcome to the stoah i am
peter limber the Stewart of the store
and the store is a place for us to
cohere and dialogue about what matters
most at the knife's edge of this moment
and today we're very lucky to have
Michael Brooks from the Michael Brooks
show I'm very excited for this one
because I want to engage more in these
sorts of talks sort of a more political
talks which is something I've been
shying away from and my friend Frank
Cooper he's on my case on this all the
time not being sort of the neutral
observer role so I'm really really
excited for this and how it's going to
work Ravens going to Ravens going to
formally introduce Michael and then and
tell us how the the Q & A is gonna work
and then and then we'll go from there
so find over to Raven great thanks Peter
so today we're gonna do a little bit of
a dialogue with Michael and then after
the 20 minute dialogue will open up to
Q&A from everybody in the session so
Michael is an independent content
producer and has a couple different
shows that he works with he's working
with jacques Abin he has writing and it
works on their show there he's on the
majority report and also has his show
the Michael Brooks show where he's had
slab Boise Jack on Lulu de Silva lots of
interesting figures so we're really
excited to have him today he recently
just wrote a book called against the web
and I hope that we can get into the
content for that one
so Michael welcome to the stoah I meet
yourself sir I didn't realize I was
muted apologies it's good to be here
guys thanks so much
so initially could you just give us some
texts for the work that you do and what
what you're what you're doing here today
well I guess I'm here to talk about my
book and I'm in other things and I'm
interested in how my work can connect in
ways that are productive with people
that are interested I guess in
consciousness for lack of a better word
so I'm interested in building those
bridges and Brent is a great facilitator
of that so I want to give props to him
and also Jeremy Johnson there's another
person in this world that whose work I
really appreciate I am a talk show host
essentially and I you know my primary
vehicle is the Michael Brooks show a lot
of the focus of that show is on
international relations on trends in
global politics I definitely am coming
from sort of of Marxist left looking at
things trying to look at things in a
very material and historical way and
figure out a better way of going into
the future by actually being much more
grounded in the past so I think a lot of
the work that I try to do is very
historically oriented particularly the
longer forms and more deep dives and one
of the ways it actually intersects with
the books with the of the book is really
in feeling like a lot of kind of pop
intellectual culture right now doesn't
have a historical ground and if we can
start to have a historical grounding of
things we can have a much more dynamic
opportunities for building a better
political culture so yeah so Michael
Brooks show is probably the primary I
mean that's my show that's my vehicle so
that's probably the best way to really
track what I'm doing but yeah I also do
the show with Anna for Jacobin and you
could see me in a bunch of other outlets
with with you know and and I think with
what some some people might think to be
some kind of contradictory impulses but
that's the synthesis like on one hand
really trying to make a show that is
grounded in a certain type of realism
and attempt to look at the world as sort
of clearly and dispassionately as
possible in some ways taking power
really seriously and how power works and
then also at the same time thinking that
we need to get that that's some of the
kind of questions that come from
I guess spiritual places are relevant as
well so sort of like yeah I think what
was some person my show was described
one time as like was like unwell Cal
Jazeera yeah
and or which is interesting Alok
aljazeera I love al-jazeera what they
are run you know it's already monarchy
or you know marks and Machiavelli meets
you know Howard Stern and mindfulness so
that's kind of a flavor but yeah that's
and I'm I'm interested in these kind of
conversations that I think could be
productive bridge-building yeah so we
yeah cuz I mean you just had dr. Cornel
West on and he's a revolutionary
Christian and you had a wonderful
conversation about the role of
spirituality and in politics and the
fact that I think largely it's missing
and that that's something that stood out
to me that makes you kind of a unique
figure on the left to be talking about
the spiritual elements of politics but
before we get into that I'd like you to
describe the thesis of your book and
kind of the framework of your criticism
of the IDW look and in some ways the
book I mean you know the please you
should definitely go buy the book it's a
very good book but I'll do a confession
that you know anytime you write a book
and a privilege and frustration you can
go either way of doing live content
multiple times a week is that on one
hand I mean you know there's a lot of
content out there plenty of room to make
mistakes and think you could do things
better but on the other hand it allows
you to evolve day to day you know and so
to me I mean this is a cast
characters that I guess I was a lot more
interested in frankly when I started the
book these folks don't occupy much of my
attention right now but the primary
thing that I was interested in and then
when I got contracted to do the book was
was one that I felt that these guys
definitely were selling an eight
historical worldview and that's a very
big theme for me I I think you cannot
pray or hope or anything to understand
big questions about the economy about
why things look the way they look today
without looking at things in a
historical process and I and and the
reason that I refer to all of these guys
is being somewhere on the right in my
view even though I get that some of them
are you know Democrats or whatever but
in a broader sense of understanding
politics what is your kind of frame you
know for how you what is your starting
point for understanding things right and
I think broadly a left project looks at
the material and historical forces as to
why we are where we're at and how those
things are operating and I think that
various right-wing projects and by the
way in my view there's some projects
that might appeal appears superficially
very whoa in quote-unquote progressive
that actually are quite conservative
because what they're trying to do is
either naturalize things as a scientific
process or mythologize things so you
know you look at a lot of these folks
and my first big kind of collision with
these guys with sam Harris's writing on
on islam and you know yeah III guess I
had objections that people would kind of
expect on some sort of liberal grounds
that I think he was you know kind of me
definitely being an asshole about it and
that there was very troubling
implications from a policy perspective
what he was writing and talk about what
he was writing and advocating but even
more broadly was just the way that that
somebody thought that they could take on
such an incredibly complicated terrain
and I mean like really like stuff that
you could spend as a scholar two or
three years trying to understand what
happened in Afghanistan from like 86 to
93 as a launching point for maybe
scratching the surface of understanding
the rise of a group like Isis and really
thinking that you could skip over so
much just reality in history and kind of
substitute thought experiments and a few
opinion polls and and some quotes from
some holy books that that just kind of
offended me intellectually and I felt
that like and then Jordan Peterson came
along and and I think the thing that
caught me with Peterson was that you
know and as you said I especially I
guess for somebody on the left I'm not
allergic to the spiritual stuff for the
interest in mythology I thought his
basic framework was kind of boring and I
didn't think it was particularly
convincing but I thought what was
interesting about him and this is what
leads to the what made the book more
exciting for me to write was that he was
speaking to so many serious and urgent
needs and I think he was you know miss
diagnosing them I you know again I
didn't find his product the name of the
chapter on him in the book is the dragon
who didn't do his homework so that gives
you a sense of where I'm coming from in
terms of of you know my sort of how
impressed I am with his work but he was
talking about serious stuff he's talking
about alienation he was talking about
lack of meaning he was talking about
really really urgent things and the
response from the sort of conventional
liberal sort of media was just to kind
of point out the ways in which he was
wrong
empirically or historically which you
know fair enough he gets a lot wrong
there's no doubt about it you know he
confuses Marxism with post-modernism in
a way that like honestly like any intro
to history of philosophy class would
clear up for you but that wasn't really
the point the point was the themes he
was speaking to and and if we didn't
have a way of addressing those needs
then you know we would just be kind of
you know failed more
lasers which is oftentimes so much of
what kind of liberal politics basically
is and so I got interested in the book
in terms of okay how can I answer what I
think the mistakes these guys are making
in ways that are bigger than them
because I think that the models that
they're using that even if they go away
which they kind of have they're still
gonna be replicated in other ways this
kind of impulse to take big complex
problems and reduce them down to simple
stories then I was also but then I also
was like yeah I mean clearly I think
part of the reason they have so much
resonance is because people in the sort
of pop intellectual culture who
represent the quote-unquote left don't
have very compelling answers to some of
these things and they have their own
sort of boring repetitive moralistic
narratives and so I I kind of saw it as
an opportunity to address them and then
create what I think is a much more
compelling and dynamic and appropriate
for being in such a globalized time kind
of vision of what the left could be so
that that's what the book was trying to
do excellent and so I think this is
thank you yeah well yeah I enjoyed it
myself
and I found that I think I agree with
you in the sense that you know when you
get into a group of people and
especially in response to a historical
event which I think that the culture
wars and what was happening on campuses
generally was like there was people on
the Left who were involved in things and
then suddenly this these this activity
started and it started to kind of split
right in in left leftist politics and in
meta modernism and in other groups of
people in this in this world and a lot
of people went reactionary alongside the
IDW so one of the things that I'm
curious about is now that that kind of
hype I think has passed generally and
now we're being pressed upon with more
existential threats I mean the the
feeling that politics is is important is
really coming to the fore even for
people who thought that maybe they could
be apolitical during this time what
would you say to people who went
reactionary during this phase in order
to bring them into what I think you call
Finland station or cosmopolitan
socialism and maybe describe what those
two things are as well yeah so that's so
basically what I used in the book is a
framework and again these and I think
people probably miss conversation will
be more comfortable than sometimes I do
interviews and I know a certain
audiences are hyper literalistic which
is a problem definitely 90w scene and
also in a lotta they know some of the
left scene as well but I don't I don't
mean these and they weren't originally
meant as you know these are not precise
scientific definitions but they they
indicate different ways of being in the
world looking at politics so watch
Carson Carra has a collaborative mind he
found the Jackman magazine talked about
Singapore station hungry station and
Finland station as three basically you
know three basic models of how to relate
to politics and Singapore is the world
outpost of a certain type of neoliberal
projects and if you look at anything
from Fried's acharya to Davos to Thomas
Friedman again it's not literally that
people want to be Singapore but what
Singapore valorizes what Singapore has
succeeded in and what Singapore also
does not include is is really the kind
of end point of a certain type of
technocratic neoliberalism there is some
degree of of tolerance and respect and
openness people are judged along really
their performance and contribution to
the market system there's a real I mean
there's it's no mistake that you know
Singapore is the one that's testing the
robotic dog from Boston Dynamics you
know to friendly you know gently remind
people of public parts that keep social
distance you see this in the mayorship
of Bloomberg in New York and and it's
you know people know their place and
people fit in a technocracy and there is
some room to advance you know along a
market hierarchy
potentially and and and again whether or
not we're talking about places that are
formerly kind of managed non-democracies
or even the way a lot of you know I mean
Thomas Friedman in the late 90s has a
famous phrase the called the golden
straitjacket where he says look you can
have elections and we can you know have
competitive marketplace of politics but
if you don't have core economic rules in
place that situate you for globalization
you're out of the game and that that is
a very you know that's a core kind of
Singapore statement then hungry station
represents this rise of these new kind
of neo authoritarian right-wing leaders
that people talk about a lot this is you
know Paulson ro and Trump and Horeb on
and so on and you know there's again
there's another thing you can make
distinctions between these different
people in the different ways they're
historically situated but for purposes
of this they represent a kind of wanting
to go back into the past an imagined
community of the past a backlash in some
ways against social liberalism but
really a strong defense of market and
capitalist activity as well but wanting
to preserve basically various types of
you know in the Americas case say like a
white identitarian politics along with
that market formulation and Finland
station represents you know Lenin on his
way back before the Soviet revolution
and and and again this is not about
getting into a big debate about the
Soviet Union and what it was and all of
this but that revolutionary activity and
the proper reading of Marx is that it's
a fulfillment of an expansion of
democracy project the idea was that just
as the sort of Divine Right of Kings was
interrogated in the political realm
people need a great deal of more agency
and power over their own economic lives
and and and you know the events of 1917
are extraordinary I mean that level of
public participation and energy for the
idea that you're going to get rid of a
feudal system
and also get rid of kind of a
discredited parliamentary you know not
that you wouldn't still have a democracy
but that you would have a substantive
democracy is is dynamic and important
and so the argument of the book is
really that the IDW and a lot of
right-wing politics represents different
there and a lot of our world politics
today represents a conflict between
Singapore and hungry and we need more
Finland and so I I think two people
who've been really caught in the IDW I
guess and and kind of reactionary
politics I guess I would say on one hand
that's made me more inviting is that
there you can tune into a much bigger
world of politics today and find much
more dynamic and compelling answers and
maybe some of the things that put you
off to kind of pop liberal discourse
that that these kind of too simplistic
things are not the choice it isn't you
know you don't have to listen to IDW
guys you know freaking out about trans
people and endlessly whining about
political correctness and you don't need
to I don't know go and read the top ten
reasons that Seinfeld is problematic or
whatever the hell it is that was going
on in in you know trash kind of pop woke
culture that there are people who are
really doing work to try to understand
why we are where we are today and I
think you know again some of the
manifestations of this are things like
you know Bernie Sanders and so on which
particularly the United States having an
agenda basic universal decency that has
never been achieved here is really
significant there's also people who are
trying to understand and the
cosmopolitan component is you know these
guys have this fixation on this
mythological idea of the West is the
last thing I'll say I think they've in
various ways particularly Peterson I
guess Ben Shapiro too although I mean
obviously I take him less seriously but
they have this very romantic and a
historical idea of what the West is now
the Clapp now the sort of
shallow woke response to that is to say
well no like screw the West the West has
always been evil the West has always
been corrupt the my response and the
response to the tradition I'm in whether
it's CLR James or Cornel West or Adolph
read or fat's among ran EC or people
like this is to say well first of all
the quote unquote West is is literally
an a historical concept there is no
unbroken chain from Greece to today and
even when we go back to Greece we're
already talking about a society that was
pan Asian and African had a variety of
influences from its inception and Anna a
great tradition that of course we should
be reading along with everywhere else in
the world and the way this this sort of
links up and the last example I'll give
is in the 1990s there was a really big
debate on something called Asian values
and these were countries that actually
are going to be they're coming back into
the discourse because or bond is very
he'll say specifically he's influenced
by some of the conversations that we're
having in Malaysian Singapore in the 90s
and in this time of like big triumphal
ism in the post-cold war world
there was three there were these two
positions and one was that you know you
have to get on board with the Western
model of democracy and quote-unquote
human rights and these certain Asian
leaders like Lee Kuan Yew would saying
no that's ridiculous
we have our own conception of human
rights with our own conception of how we
do society right because we come from a
different value tradition and a bit very
big influence on me Amartya Sen is an
Indian economist and philosopher and he
was at Oxford at the time and he said
you know this is a ludicrous debate
because the the Western chauvinists are
acting as if they have invented and
again in this a historical flow like
from Socrates to Clinton we came up with
human rights we came up with democracy
we nailed it everybody should just copy
us and then these Asian values leaders
are
miss reading their own traditions to
justify their own autocratic practices
and actually what you can do is you can
easily have a reading of Confucianism or
Indian philosophy or African you know
that that's that talked about holding
that talk about transparency that talk
about open dialogue that you can fit
into a broader quest for quote unquote
human rights so the sort of answer was
there are universal aspirations there
are universal things joining people but
they don't come from one source so in
other words and it's interesting because
a lot of these arguments track today on
both the left and the right right you'll
see on the right this kind of RIA
surgence of Western chauvinism which
again is a historical and particularly
in 2020 it's showing in the 1990s it was
triumphant in 2020 it's very insecure
because China's rising and this just
doesn't fit with the world as it works
and looks today
but then on both the populous right and
this neo nationalism where there's
obsessions with the nation-state
there's the these fixation on the idea
that there are distinct communities and
they can't necessarily overlap and
healthy open democracies and then even
on parts the left that pushed so far
into identitarian politics that from us
from like standpoint epistemology it's
like we can never we can never overlap
on anything because our experiences are
too different so all we have to do is
sit on platform capitalist platforms of
you know from Silicon Valley and you
know berate each other or hear each
other or recognize each other we can
never have a tangible common project and
so I thought sin was so relevant and I
connected it with my own really strong
orientation towards labor politics and
the things that everybody needs
regardless of where they are health care
housing greater power over their
economic lives but that this this end
model was so relevant because people are
rightfully wanting to have their own
narratives about
our s democracy and things like that
rooted in narratives that aren't just
the usual Western ones that's a correct
impulse and they want an na and it's one
that's showing up on both the left and
right in very different ways and you
can't just dismiss that but then on the
other hand we actually need to hold the
idea that in fact there are Universal
commonalities there are similarities
there are shared impulses there are
shared trajectories and the best way to
recognize that is by actually being
truly global in that sense so that
you're you know you're in a process of
addition not subtraction thank you so
when I open up questions from the chat
so if you have any questions for Michael
go ahead and put them in there and I'll
call on you and you can unmute your mic
but until somebody asks a question I
wanted to ask you so we're talking about
like this kind of universal value which
of course goes against the idea of
post-modernism so you can't really lump
you into a postmodern perspective
because we have this idea that but also
that there's this multipolarity right
that this idea of Human Rights shows up
in cultures in various places at various
times in history is there is there some
connection to spirituality here do you
do you think that the there's a
relationship between kind of fighting
for this higher limit of human freedom
and also spiritual practice it certainly
is in some places I mean you know one of
the kind of funny positions that I'm in
is that some of my critique of
standard-issue Western liberalism comes
because I am you know very interested in
and trying as best as possible to be
engaged with other places so you know
Brazil is a place that's very important
to me president Lula was the world's
most important political prisoner I had
the you know great honor of going to
somme Paulo and interviewing him and you
know you can't you can't understand I
mean you can't understand the Workers
Party certainly without understanding
trade unionism and socialism and you
also can't understand
without understanding Liberation
Theology so I I don't so to me you know
regardless of whether or not you're
personally engaged that way there just
needs to be a much more mature and
cosmopolitan conversation about religion
spirituality in the different ways of
manifests I think what this book
potentially could point to I don't go
into it but I think that a corollary
with understanding that intellectual and
political movements are in relationship
like I just I just was watching a great
interview with the former president of
South Africa table and Becky who was
talking about that when he was
organizing in Europe as the information
minister for the African National
Congress against apartheid how it was
really striking being in Ireland because
he would see you know he would
he was like yeah we needed everybody's
you know help and it was great but the
conversation in London was different you
know in Dublin they had books for me to
read that were relevant for how we were
building our own strategies and I and
that to me is is incredibly inspiring
but even beyond that I think that it
could point to you know if you're if
we're in a process of an addition not
subtraction I think people's ways of
relating and being in the world
existentially and and in terms of
individual community could be relevant
so that to me does point to the validity
of being open to spiritual experiences
and how they interact with people's
approach to politics and and and those
and those quests that we were talking
about so I I think it's possible I mean
I I also don't also will say like I I
think post-modernism has become kind of
a stand-in for you know the the work of
questioning power narratives and how
things get naturalized it isn't like
that isn't the primary home of my
politics but I could tell you that you
know if you had to read Foucault love
him or hate him or dairy
whenever in college you pretty quickly
got that this wasn't the same as
somebody going you that's just like your
opinion man like it's very demanding
stuff so I do want to note that too and
I actually think another thing that is
being reacted to that I guess in this
bunch like Harris really exemplifies
even though he has this kind of funny
you know he's a promoter of meditation
but I I think a very like flatland
approach to reality that has no
distinction making when it comes to
certainly spirituality and religion
right that it's all just quote/unquote
untrue and that's all you need to know
and that got to me again just even sort
of anthropologically I don't like I
don't know what what does the truth
claims of the Bible have to do with
liberation of theology in the Union
Building in San Bernardino like it it's
totally irrelevant and it shrinks your
worldview in in really disastrous ways
for you know understanding how things
work great thank you for the answer
Peter would you like to and meet
yourself yeah so let me see how I'm
gonna formulate this a question is
around sort of like strategy outreach
for political ideas and as I mentioned
in the beginning Brent's always on my
case like Peter you got the more
political that more political and I
guess he's right in this thinking it was
just listening to you speak it's like a
lot of this feels above my paygrade
right and I know if I did my homework if
I just sat down and just like read it
I'm like yeah yeah I could I could rock
it and just thinking about that
resistance I have to even want to engage
in politics it's like what you said it's
like there's like it's like they're
trying to manipulate my emotions all the
times like this scintillating like on
the the social justice warriors shaming
you for being a white male than the
intellectual dork web attacking you for
this or that for not being based enough
and I just like okay fuck off you know I
just do this go away
like in my stoicism kicks in and my reps
there and I just wanna case of distance
I think in that act it's like I almost
the whole cat
Corie of politics I push away and I
don't want to engage in it so I guess to
tease out a question there is how to
ethical ego about talking about these
very important issues that you're
talking about in such a way that's
attractive to people like me and I'll
imagine someone who's met have a met
awareness of this a lot of people's
don't so I guess what is your current
strategy or what is a good strategy to
go about that well I mean you know
that's that's ever-evolving right and
and also you don't know I mean one of
the things that's funny to me about this
whole terrain is like you know again I
mean you see this with I guess you know
some of these IDW characters and all day
like oh like don't be a snowflake and
meanwhile you know oh my god you
criticize the guy but I liked his books
I'm gonna have like a three weeks mental
breakdown and you know harass you on
Twitter so I think we got that I think
you actually have to distinguish between
form and substance right so you know and
and again I don't really I I find that
sort of like very basic pop cultural
politics debate to be incredibly boring
and there are moments where it's like
you know I don't know what to say
like arguing about nonsense and the
things that are going to actually drive
and are driving our world today whether
we're talking about pandemics or 5g or
arms control or you having healthcare
like you know there is that phrase of
like politics is interested in you
regardless of whether you're interested
in it so I think you have to make a
really big distinction there then I
think you know I'd make a distinction
between you know a mediocre
representation of ideas that might have
some validity and some relevance versus
something that is just sort of you know
hacky and redundant but you know I don't
know as far as as far as communicating
these ideas it's very difficult because
I've I've as an example
I've had feedback from some people that
say like oh you got me much more engaged
in politics in fact you changed my
politics because the show is
intellectually open and whatever but
it's also funny it also has a certain
attitude to it it's also in entertaining
I see other people who you know I don't
know I did some impression of Jordan
Peterson like 18 months ago and they are
unable to watch an interview with Cornel
West they're so emotionally distraught
by that and so you know in my own
process it's a it's a dialectic you know
sometimes I get the feedback feedback
around you know sort of what you're
saying and my response is like
ironically it's kind of just like Jesus
dude I don't know what to say man up
like read a fucking book like this
should not be so like heavy it shouldn't
be so like emotionally dramatic like
take some of that stoicism and write out
a few uncomfortable conversations and
get engaged in this stuff like read the
Financial Times this is real and you
know it extremely real and then on you
know on the other hand I'm very
cognizant and very aware that so much
communication from from both honestly
you know politics that are just not my
politics but I recognize will get put in
the sort of same basket but they're not
my politics and even people with you
know with my politics there's there's
folks that are absolutely brilliant and
incredible but you know it's either the
you know it requires like a theory like
a serious theoretical background to
engage with or it's just kind of you
know it just isn't immediately
accessible and so I think those are
really valid concerns and I'm not always
sure how to address them I mean like
I've tried to think of one aspect is can
the stuff be fun and entertaining the
other aspect is what can I learn from
somebody like Cornel West in terms of
just like the energy of the precinct
you know he's like a really big hero of
mine although also I do think with some
of these people whether it's Mike about
Cornell west or Loula or whatever I mean
you know we can apprentice these people
but that's gonna come with age you know
like you're never gonna be able to
project that kind of like I don't know
you there's so much work that that needs
to be done internally and externally but
you can you know I can model the best
and then that third you know that I
think I think people I think people I
think bringing people in through you
know again I'll mention Lula you know I
think people have gotten a pretty good
understanding some things that were
happening in Brazil through this heroic
story and you know it's a story of a
person that opens up a big pneumatic
range and you know the last thing I'll
say is I definitely on my show and
definitely what I'm trying to push
people towards are you know people like
Adolf Reid who's a huge influence on me
you have massive respect for it and you
know his writing on essentialism and
economics and identitarian politics it's
like it isn't even just that it is
neither
I guess the SJW stuff that you're
responding to or this kind of
embarrassing IDW stuff it's it's like
actual politics it's just it's it's like
it's not only as a trend sending that
today that's like a couple of sophomores
in high school throwing food at each
other and I'm recommending that you read
like a seasoned labor organizer and pen
professor who has developed a model
since like the 60s that really makes a
lot of sense and is very historically
grounded so I think some of it is just
and and maybe I take some patience but
some of that stuff is you know that
stuff is demanding it isn't just like a
Twitter argument right let's require to
read things but it's a lot more
rewarding yeah so like um here's my
assessment let me know if you think I
got it correct and I see I see too like
Michael Brooks and I know when I lose in
our kind of mutual hero Cornel West in
the moment but there's one that like
right now there's like your arguments
are credibly
cogent your coherent like this fucking
tight and you don't want to fuck with
you in a debate hit so that's like we
saw with it was Sargon and then and then
there's and then there's there's that
kind of like that that devilish michael
brooks come up with like sam harris
comes at the same harris his name comes
up you just fucking like go off there
upon him and i kind of like it too
because you know he kind of uh annoys me
a little bit but like you said they said
there's like there's like a bifurcation
because there's people who like sam
harris like a pair of social
relationship that they had with him and
they could get triggered in the wrong
way or they might get seduced the right
way and I see you just being authentic I
just see you being you and then you have
these two personalities but you like you
said our mutual hero West like like
Trump is ideological component brother
Trump like the guy is like just you feel
his ideas are coming from a place of
love and so I don't know if there's a
question here but like I guess how do we
be more like West or how do we get guys
like West to be more influential less
this pretty influential but right I mean
I think the the the the tricking what
you're saying though and again this is a
funny thing because I see this both you
know certainly in a lot of places on the
Left like oh I can't you be nice you
know or whatever and I see this in a lot
of places on the on the right frankly I
mean Cornel West it isn't just the
Donald Trump is his ideological opponent
he says he's a fascist and a gangster
and a existential threat to humanity I
mean this guy is so clear and he's got
his spiritual practice of deeply
recognizing a shared humanity with even
the worst of us so I actually think that
what Cornel West is doing and in my and
what I will aspire to do and fall short
on constantly definitionally is a space
that is completely missing from these
conversations and we need to figure out
a way to build which is on one hand
there is a soft indulgent culture that
is not at all exclusive to the left I
see it in every space where people
cannot deal with criticism
they can't deal with rigor they can't
deal with having their ideas
interrogated and then conversely I
people completely dehumanize each other
to the point where I actually start to
see why the stakes feel so intense
because if you were if we actually had a
culture where we recognize that we're
all human beings who have made mistakes
we'll make mistakes maybe sometimes even
serious mistakes get things wrong and
that there was a process around
evolution and rebuilding instead of
tearing down and destruction I think
people's anxiety levels will go down a
lot more so I you know I I think that
it's a really hard process and this is
something that I'm thinking about a lot
more recently I don't exactly know how
to engage with it but I will say I
noticed people people skip the sides of
the equation like some people say like
oh you know Cornel West kills him with
kindness and it's so great the way he
called somebody a brother before he like
rips them and it you know and beats the
shit out of them and then spiritual
people are like oh man it's so great the
way he does that it's like he's doing
both yeah I agree
and he's really doing both and so I
think the question is is you know how do
we cultivate a culture that allows for
both and maybe honestly I you know I do
think some of these social media
platforms you know not necessarily I
think obviously being able to do a show
in these new podcasts and YouTube
vehicles or whatever is incredibly lucky
and interesting it has its own problems
but I do think the kind of I just don't
ever think there's any way of generating
a healthy Twitter discourse as an
example I think it really does lend
itself to exactly the wrong kind of
incentive structure so yeah I think you
know look and I can totally say with
regards to San Harris like I you know
and again I find this to be another
interesting tension I don't like him
I
I find the world view the presentation
you know I think it's actually
incredibly mediocre and I think it's
attached to like an extraordinary kind
of arrogance I don't like it but I also
of course I definitely had to ask myself
I don't know what the answers are you
know I don't know why that pisses me off
so much at times though you know again
already I'm sure the way I talk about
these guys today is different than I
talked about them in two years ago maybe
even a year ago as I'm in my own process
so I think that if you want that Cornel
West face it's gonna embrace a really
interesting contradiction because it's
gonna involve so much more actual
tolerance and so much more actual
ability but then and and forgiveness and
open this but it's also going to be a
lot more rigorous I mean one of the
things in that interview that was so fun
that he did was you know he was praising
my book which was blowing my mind and he
had this great line which I don't know
how many people caught but it was like
this beautiful slight dig at the people
I'm writing about and that me raised
like you know it's a great book he goes
you know these aren't the most profound
brothers that you talk on beautiful like
a little bit like yeah great you ran
circles around these guys like you
humble and even bit of things like you
didn't take on like play-doh
Edmund Burke that's true that's a very
good point and then but then also what a
great shade on them yeah yeah I mean
that's again I think sometimes we just
gotta you know we talked about the
Jordan documentary earlier I mean so we
just got to watch and prototype the best
people Thanks yeah behind it back to
Raven but we're just come to mind is you
know printable meta modern movement they
call it philosophical allergies and I
just certain like people ideology just
trigger you don't know why like sam
harris like i might my read on the
others like this is a concealed
arrogance just the performance there and
it just annoys me like I feel like
annoyance in my body when when I might
hear him talk even though I can like you
stoic enough to separate in this ease
there's good ideas for what they are
like the meditation stuff and whatnot
and what we're doing here at the stola
is sort of developing like what for
baekje calls memory Kia called you have
practices like a wisdom gym that's the
cute word we're running with but where
you can kind of like develop these
cogent coherent arguments arguments not
compromise them but still like sink into
the felt sense level and become embodied
and come from a place of love and
there's like not an answer for that like
how to do that successfully but I really
appreciate your being you know at the
edge here with that with us great Brent
please share your lung question thank
you actually you guys covered quite you
anticipated and and said a lot so I can
kind of a bridge my question but if I
may to address Peters question about
politics I just wanted to say like like
in my view it's not about knowing what's
horse to back because that's complicated
it's about knowing what correct policies
to advocate for first and then knowing
which horse to back to deliver them
right so in that context like it should
be clear like Medicare for all is not
debatable right because health care is a
human right mm um so my question was
along the lines of you know how we can
do better and this session is a huge
step in that direction you know I wanted
to say quickly like I love I love the
comedy stuff too but that's not for
everybody right the dunking has its
limit um hmm and so sort of by way of
analogy
carlos masa was on the surfs and i i
asked what he thought of the ezra klein
ben shapiro interview and he said he
hadn't seen it but he gave a great
answer which was you know ben shapiro is
a bad actor and and basically Ezra Klein
is a naive actor so of course it's gonna
fail on those grounds to have any
traction or to change anybody's minds
and and and likewise behind the scenes
with the IDW there's lots of connections
between people and we could actually
break this down quicker
mmm if we tried to
some of the question was you know along
those lines like what can we do to
accelerate the process because we're
sort of running out of time with climate
change was the political crisis and and
the whole IDW thing you know I say all
the time like like look on one hand
maybe it had to happen but it just felt
like a huge waste of time and a huge
distraction and and however much
ostensibly liberal they might identify
right there they're kind of pseudo
intellectual discourse helps facilitate
more trumpism right even if Ben Shapiro
is anti Trump it facilitates more
trumpism so you know that the task is
for for people to dramatically change
their minds in terms of metanoia
and you know there's people like Peter
Dow who's a great example of that he's
very self-conscious about his
transformation from from from a Hillary
Clinton advocate to a big Bernie
surrogate um and there's there's a few
other people but it's rare you know I
mean and just another little anecdote
about bad actors a friend I'm just going
to jump in there's other people that
have questions so maybe yes you got a
question here yeah
wrapping it up yeah Sam Harris is a bad
actor if there's any salience to this
concept of meta modernism I emailed Sam
Harris in 2016 from a supportive stance
to say hey would this interest you and
and he never got back to me Noam Chomsky
got back to me within an hour
right so it's and there are people there
to people who have clashed so my
question just is what what can we do
better uh to Michael into all of us to
Peter you know how can we accelerate
this process I think that the one thing
that I would just move off of briefly
from that is I read a lot of Ken Wilber
when I was younger I was a big ken
wilber guy and he was helpful for
practice ideas and you know I was doing
my like meditate and then take a run
ken wilber guy but you know and I did
but I was studying international
relations and again it wasn't that his
writing on politics
I certainly disagreed with but it was
also just like it wasn't it wasn't
credible like I'm just trying to think
of an analogous field it was just like
okay look I know enough that this guy is
not reading the people in the literature
he's not reading so I think one thing
with with something like meta modernism
it's very helpful to really start now I
look obviously I have my politics so I
know who I think the best people are but
in along with with dr. West joke it's
like if you want to build a meta modern
framework you have to make sure that the
people that you're plugging into it are
actually really good at what they're
doing so I think that if you're saying
like okay we're going to try to
synthesize you know East and West left
and right and then your examples are
like oh I you know I'm picking some like
random cult leader from India and some
like liberal columnist for The New York
Times and some like you know new atheist
guru you're missing people that might
represent things from analogous
perspectives in all of those spaces that
are a lot more demanding and a lot more
sophisticated and again cuz like I keep
thinking of this Adolph read example
because there's so many arguments that I
see that take place in this kind of
cultural terrain that I know that it's
like he just covers them better and it's
not even a question of like yeah of
course you know he would come down on
one slide or another things but he
genuinely transcends this debate if you
want to take that on then you got to
read stuff that is analogous level to
him to take on so I I think part of
accelerating the process is making sure
that the sources we have are good and
that's one of the things that I did that
I liked about doing this book too is
just honestly alternative like these are
more interesting people to read it's
more interesting to read cabral it's
more interesting to read Adolf read and
it's more interesting to read
you know people that are really engaged
in this stuff so yeah that's that's
where I would start
but I'll wrap it up so we can get a few
more in great it looks like maybe we
could get in one more question before
you know guys I actually could I can go
like another 10 or 15 I did this thing I
have another thing but it's less tight
than I thought it was so we can you know
we can go a touch longer okay that's
excellent so yeah we'll cover one final
question and we'll let you answer it to
your leisure let's see here so Ron we
are getting to your question would you
like thank you and you may have touched
on this already Michael but I'm pardon
if there's a little rambling you know
coming in I definitely had resistance to
the idea that Harris and Peterson
particularly are on the right so to
speak I know how they look that way
under maybe our current political
categories and lenses and and whatnot
and I'm very into the meta modern stuff
I would say just so you know my
perspective and we had a thing on that
just a couple hours ago
and I look at someone like Peterson I
can't say about Harris as a meta modern
phenomena in many ways and interestingly
as I'm listening to you today and I find
I'm having way less resistance to your
talk that I thought I might have had
coming in so that's always a pleasant
surprise and usually people who identify
as being in the left eye I sometimes
will find I have a resistance but I'm
finding your your overall approaching
vibe whether you think this way is meta
modern to me so I wonder so for my
strange political ends admittedly I
almost look at someone like Peterson and
yourself as both meta modern in many
ways and different threads of that
widely you know viewed and that maybe
need to come together and clash and
tweak and work out stuff so does that
click with you at all that maybe in some
ways some of these guys that you have
the differences with you're all part of
something that a modern national like
that's emerging and just needs to be
worked out a lot
stuff needs to be worked out I mean I
guess I look because I I don't know if I
think we're Jordan Peterson is and a lot
of this rain that I talk about
politically he is objectively on the
right and that's not like a problem per
se I I frankly don't I'm not into the
not saying where you are part so if you
go to meet with or bond and this is a
guy you know to be clear there's a lot
of melodrama in conversations Victor
Oregon a couple of weeks ago like
formally you know temporarily has
suspended democracy and hungry he's gone
further than and there's a lot of
tendencies this way certainly with
Boston ro and definitely in some key
ways with Trump when Jordan Peterson
flies there and hangs out with him and
they kind of have a you know complain
about liberal college professors fest
the most generous thing I could do is
that he is not in the world and does not
understand the dynamics he's playing
with and III think that that is a really
big problem so again part of what I
would go to is I I think if we started
from a very different baseline and we
recognize because I certainly like
Brent's my perspective is with friend
like if we're talking about the United
States
I guess the policies an agenda that
would be identified as like the
quote-unquote left to achieve those
things like completing the New Deal
getting everybody health care I mean
these things aren't in any kind of
global sense would be centrist and they
are morally obvious and I think
confusing them is really problematic I
think that there are people that
interest me more frankly than Peterson
but who do speak in similar terrain I
mean he's passed
if James Hillman was still around I
would be really excited to interview him
I think his work on article psychology
was
fascinating and it actually can it
integrated with a very interesting
critique of psychotherapy sort of the
opposite of Peterson's which is that
psychotherapists are getting tasked with
solving problems that are socially
generated they mean this in a very broad
sense you know yeah a lot a lot of
really good like yeah course there's
depression and it was high tea in the
culture we're living in you know you're
you're there's a lot to be sort of upset
about and he managed that with also a
very clear discourse on I guess what
will be called personal responsibility
ascot at Hren is an ethnographer who has
actually studied and worked with the
United Nations and various other
agencies terrorism like in a real way
and has talked from an anthropological
perspective about the loss of meaning
and sacred value drives and how they
relate to why people join groups like
this so Peterson not so much and maybe I
also I guess I also I think met Amman is
important but I also looked at things
kind of dialectically so I think that
there was this vacuum in the culture
that he came in and filled and
necessarily someone had to fill that I
wish it was filled better right i but I
think that maybe the vibe they're
getting from me and where I'm much more
receptive and I hope it comes across is
that the train he is on in some key
areas is a totally valid terrain even as
I would have you know a pretty tough
critique of him but I think that if
you're interested in meaning purpose
these types of things I don't of course
we all should be interested in these
types of things I I hope that answers
your question somewhat and I and I
totally think that in the you know in a
bit
it goes back to what I was saying to
Brent to of course there can be really
big there I don't think it's that
everybody has the same perspective or
the same politics but I think there is
base
lines of sophistication that you have to
clear first just as like conversely I
you know I didn't write a chapter saying
that Jordan Peterson doesn't know
anything about Jung know I'll cede that
to him but he should see politics to me
[Laughter]
excellent and with that as our learning
final statements you'd like to say
Michael before we close up the session
it's just an honor it's a it's a real
pleasure and I look forward to it some
more if you guys want to collaborate
more and I'm Raven thank you and thank
you Peter and thank you Brent for
pushing this long and thanks to
everybody who participated and I hope
everybody stay safe and stay strong out
there yeah definitely I hope that we can
continue to have these conversations I
think the integration here is really
important and it's very timely so I
really appreciate you coming and kind of
provoking us to think about these issues
and of course for writing your book and
I wanted to end just with a quote from
Cornel West that I just loved from with
him which is to be a blues man in the
life of the mind I just love that so
amen yes amen to that
so Peter close us out yeah that's all
I'll make some announcements for next
events the first Michael brother Michael
thanks so much for coming on really
appreciate it
Brent thanks so much for being annoying
in my way and everyone for the questions
today and of course Raven for an
excellent and seeing today's event so
tomorrow we have unasked questions with
Nora Bateson that's at 1:00 p.m. Eastern
Time we have relational exegesis the
group papers with phrase yeah you know
I'm pronouncing your name that's at 4:00
p.m. and then radical honesty during a
pandemic with the self-help author Brad
Blanton that's at 6:00 p.m. Eastern Time
you can RCP on the website and if you're
if you're inspired to provide a gift you
can just go on the website and then
there's a checkout to get the economy
there all right everyone thanks so much